RG 062:086, Town of Montville
Montville, Records of Town of
Connecticut State Library
Town of Montville records
1891-1994
Connecticut State Library
Montville (Conn.)
15.25 cubic feet
Tax records and records created by the Mohegan Tribe and the State of Connecticut, opposing sides in the movement for federal acknowledgment.
RG062_086
Multiple
Historical Note
The town of Montville was incorporated on October 12, 1786 and was taken from New London.
Scope and Content
The records relating to the Mohegan Tribe consist primarily of copies of arguments, depositions, primary sources related to the history of the Mohegans, and a variety of secondary source materials in favor of and in opposition to federal acknowledgment. The records are generally arranged in chronological order and document the arduous struggle by the Mohegan to secure recognition through the process overseen by the Bureau of Indian Affairs. The Mohegans are the only Connecticut tribal entity to have successfully navigated the standard acknowledgment process.
The materials gathered by opposing parties in federal acknowledgment are significant not only for the massive documentation they provide on the recognition process, but also for the detail they include on the history of the Mohegan Tribe, both from primary and secondary sources. Often the same documents were used by differing parties in an attempt to demonstrate opposite conclusions.
The depositions of eighteen men and women taken between 1980 and 1983 provide a particularly revealing glimpse of identity at the beginnings of the modern struggle by the tribe to secure federal acknowledgment. Also of interest are lists of persons claiming to be Mohegan (Box 1, folder 15), Mohegan Tribe membership in 1993 (Box 4, folder 23), a family scroll of descendants of Joshua Occum (Box 2, folder 23), and Fielding family genealogy (Box 2, folder 25). The largest single quantity of records, however, consists of exhibits, e.g., copies of primary and secondary sources used by the parties to try to prove their cases.
The first document in the collection is a 1976 petition to Governor Ella Grasso from Wounded Wolf (Rowland Bishop), Chairman and the last is a copy of an August 1, 1994 written statement of Wayne D. Scott, Mayor of Montville to the U.S. Senate's Committee on Indian Affairs concerning Mohegan land claims.
These records from the Town of Montville provide invaluable documentation to researchers interested in the history of the Mohegans. The records also include materials on the unsuccessful attempt by the Golden Hill Paugussetts of southwestern Connecticut to gain federal recognition, see Boxes 5-6. included is one folder of materials related to the Schaghticoke Indians (Box 2, folder 16).
For those with a more general interest in Native Americans in the state or in other tribal entities, these papers provide valuable leads to the locations of such materials.
Related Material
The Connecticut State Archives holds voluminous documentation concerning Indian entities found in such places as the RG 001, Connecticut Archives, Indian Affairs, Series 1 and 2; RG 003, New London County court records, Papers by Subject: Indians; plus materials in RG 005, Office of the Governor; and RG 079, Department of Environmental Protection, to cite some of the most obvious sources.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Tax assessment -- Connecticut -- Montville -- Registers; Taxation -- Connecticut -- Montville -- Registers; Local taxation -- Connecticut -- Montville -- Registers; Property tax -- Connecticut -- Montville -- Registers; Mohegan Indians -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Connecticut; Indians of North America -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Connecticut; Mohegan Indian Tribe of Connecticut; Federally recognized Indain tribes
Places:
Montville (Conn.) -- Records and correspondence
Document Types:
Correspondence; Depositions; Genealogies; Petitions; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Acquisition Information
Series 2. Mohegan Tribe: The records were created by the Mohegan Tribe and the State of Connecticut, opposing sides in the movement for federal acknowledgment. These materials were collected by the Town of Montville from the Bureau of Indian Affairs and transferred to the Connecticut State Archives in 2006.
Container List
- Series 1. Tax records, 1891-1929; T000261; 9 cubic feet
  - Assessor's property books
    Lists real estate, animals owned, outbuildings, power boats and cars, pianos, and trade and merchandise.
    - 1910-1911, 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    - 1918-1920 (Box 2)
    - 1921-1923 (Box 3)
    - 1924-1926 (Box 4)
    - 1927-1929 (Box 5)
  - Tax abstracts
    Tax abstracts for 1923 to 1929 are not boxed.
    - 1891, 1893, 1894, 1895 (Box 6)
    - 1896, 1897, 1898, 1899-1900 (Box 7)
    - 1901, 1902, 1903, 1904, 1905 (Box 8)
    - 1906, 1907, 1908, 1909, 1910 (Box 9)
    - 1911, 1912, 1913, 1914, 1915 (Box 10)
      On oversize shelving.
    - 1916, 1917, 1918, 1919 (Box 11)
    - 1920, 1921, 1922 (Box 12)
    - 1923, 1 volume
    - 1924, 1 volume
    - 1925, 1 volume
    - 1926, 1 volume
    - 1927, 1 volume
    - 1928, 1 volume
    - 1929, 1 volume
- Series 2. Mohegan Tribe, 1976-1994; 2007-021; 6.25 cubic feet
  - Petition to Governor from Wounded Wolf (Rowland Bishop), 1976 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - State of Connecticut, 1977-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Depositions (Box 1)
    - Jayne Fawcett, 1980 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Marcy Weaver, 1981 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Stilson Sands, 1981 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Fred G. Nelson, 1981 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Rowland Bishop, 1981 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Mildred Nelson, 1981 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gladys Tantaguidgeon, Marcy Weaver, Stilson Sands, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Shirley Dziedzic Walsh, Clifford W. Baker, Sr., Frederick E. Baker, Sr., William M. Medbury, Christine Murtha, Ernest W. Gilman, Jr., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - P. Dudley Chapman, Jr., Pauline Schultz Brown, Florence Rundell, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Victor Cholewa, Virginia H. Damon, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Persons claiming to be Mohegan, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mohegan Petition prepared by Jerome S. Griner, 1984 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Petition for Federal Recognition, 1985 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
    - Exhibits, Vol. II, 1984 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
    - Exhibits, Vol. III, 1984 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 24-27)
    - Exhibits, Vol. IV, 1984 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 28-31)
    - Exhibits, Vol. V, 1984 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - Exhibits, Vol. VI, 1984 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Exhibits, Vol. X, 1985 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
    - Exhibits, Vol. XI, 1985 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
    - Additional Narrative, Vol. IB, 1985 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Schaghticoke Indians, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Griner, Jerome S., files, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Mohegan Tribe v. State of Connecticut (Box 2)
    - Statement regarding land claims, 1989 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Other documentation, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Proposed Finding against Federal Acknowledgment, 1989 October 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Summary of Proposed Finding against Federal Acknowledgment, 1989 October 30 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Family scroll, Descendents of Joshua Occum, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ann McMullen to Bureau of Acknowledgment and Research, 1990 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fielding family genealogy, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Petition for Federal Recognition, 1990 August 30 (Box 2)
    - Response, Vol. 1, Narrative Response (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    - Respondent's Exhibits (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Response, Oral histories, Vol. II (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Response, Exhibits, Vol. III (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
    - Response, RExhibits, Vol. IV (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Response, Exhibits, Vol. IV (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Response, Exhibits, Vol. V (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bureau of Indian Affiars, Proposed Finding, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Petition for Federal Recognition, Respondent's Brief, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Exhibits, Vol. I (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
    - Exhibits, Vol. II (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Exhibits, Vol. III (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Exhibits, Vol. IV (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
    - Exhibits, Vol. V (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Exhibits, Vol. VI (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
    - Exhibits, Vol. VII (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Exhibits, Vol. VIII (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
    - Exhibits, Vol. IX (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Exhibits, Vol. IX (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Petition for Federal Recognition, Respondent State of Connecticut, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Exhibits, Vol. IA (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
    - Exhibits, Vol. IIA (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
    - Exhibits, Vol. IIIA (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Exhibits, Vol. IVA (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Exhibits, Vol. VA (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Exhibits, Vol. VIA (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
  - Petition for Federal Recognition, Final Reply, 1991 March 1 (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Regulations, Guidelines and Policies for Federal Acknowledgment, 1991 March 4 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Bureau of Indian Affairs, Procedures for Establishing that and American Indian Group Exists as an Indian Tribe, 1992 April 1 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Mohegan Church, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Mohegan Tribe v. Timothy Keeney, 1993 June 14 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Regarding a landfill.
  - Mohegan Tribe membership, 1993 July 2 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Perkins Coie correspondence and papers, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 24-26)
  - Petition for Federal Recognition, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Narratives (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Response of Mohegan Tribe (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Silverstone & Koonts, 1993 June 8 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Golden Hill Paugussett Tribe of Indians v. Lowell P. Weicker, Jr., 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4-14)
  - Golden Hill Paugussett Tribe of Indians v. Lowell P. Weicker, Jr., 1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Samish Indian Tribe v. Secretary of the Interior, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Freedom of Information Act response, 1993 December 17 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Statement of Montville Mayor Wayne D. Scott in support of Mohegan Nation of Connecticut Land Claims Settlement Act of 1994 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Duplicates (Box 7)